<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Valentina Salcedo</title>
<link>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.32</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Eating vs. eating</title>
  <link>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-09-20 Eating vs. eating/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-09-20 Eating vs. eating/cover_xl.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Is there a difference between eating because you have to and eating because you love food? I think there is, and that summer highlights this difference in a way no other season does.</p>
<p>Of course, we all need filling, nutritious meals if we are to function — at least 1,600 calories a day. But when eating becomes an experience to savor, to remember, and to share, then chewing and swallowing becomes a joy.</p>
<p>When I first moved to Italy, I was surprised by how much people talk about food. Italians don’t just eat. They love food. And they are very proud of their cuisine. It’s quite normal to hear a group of friends debating the cooking times of a recipe, or to arrive early to someone’s house to help in the kitchen, chatting while sampling appetizers as the main meal is being cooked.</p>
<p>Meals are are culture. They are lessons. Italian children learn basic cooking by observing, listening, and sometimes helping their moms.</p>
<p>Food is part of every plan, whether that is a day at the beach, a weekend trip, or a visit to a friend’s house. The questions, <em>“What should we bring? What are they making?”</em>, always come up.</p>
<p>It was summer when I arrived in Italy. I felt like I was being hugged by a mother. Within weeks, friends of friends (and even their families) knew not only my name, but also what food I liked, what I cooked, and what I absolutely couldn’t resist.</p>
<p>Here are some of the tastes that make me long for next summer:</p>
<section id="watermelon-cocktail" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="watermelon-cocktail">Watermelon cocktail</h3>
<p>Perfect for an aperitivo or BBQ. This never fails to win over friends, and is ideal in hot weather.</p>
<p>Cut a watermelon in half, scoop out the fruit, and mix it with strawberries, peaches, kiwi, grapes, sugar syrup, and vodka. Let it rest in the fridge for at least three hours (overnight is even better). Serve chilled in cups or directly from the watermelon shell.</p>
</section>
<section id="summer-salad" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summer-salad">Summer salad</h3>
<p>Great when the last thing you want is to cook. Slice ripe tomatoes, add cubes of Greek cheese, drizzle with olive oil, season with salt and pepper, and chill briefly. Fresh, quick, and satisfying.</p>
<p>Back in Colombia, food often felt like an obligation. I ate so I’d have the energy to study, but eating a meal never felt fulfilling. I was constantly in need of snacks between meals — chocolate, chips, anything quick. Cooking itself felt more burdensome than comforting. But in Italy, it’s different; here food means fried seafood with lemon, a community table where someone will serve me something that is both delicious and lovingly prepared when I am feeling too blase to cook for myself. And that has taught me to see food differently. I no longer eat to get by; I eat because food delights my senses. To eat because you love is different. Eating out of love is the life I want.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Food</category>
  <category>Culture</category>
  <guid>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-09-20 Eating vs. eating/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-09-20 Eating vs. eating/cover_xs.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="79" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Italian summer we don’t talk about</title>
  <link>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-07-28 The Italian summer we don’t talk about/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-07-28 The Italian summer we don’t talk about/cover_xl.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>If you’re a 2000s baby, you probably grew up with films like “The Lizzie McGuire Movie” or “Call Me by Your Name.” Summer flings, Vespa rides, and sunburns are often the first things that come to mind when we imagine Italy in July or August. But that’s not the whole picture for Gen Z Italians.</p>
<p>For many young Italians, these months are very intense. Some are preparing for the university entrance exams. Others are splitting their days between quick beach trips and long hours at the library. And the luckiest ones? They’re celebrating the end of this chapter with a full-blown <em>festa di laurea</em>.</p>
<p>Graduation day is one of the most anticipated moments for any university student, anywhere in the world. Unlike the stressful summer exam season, this is a time of joy and release.</p>
<p>Italian universities don’t typically host a big ceremony with caps and gowns. The event is intimate and personal. And to keep things exciting, on the same day there’s still one final hurdle: defending your thesis in front of friends, family, and a panel of professors, who announce your final grade on the spot. Only then are you officially <em>laureato</em> (you hold a degree).</p>
<p>These spontaneous celebrations can last for hours, or until everyone loses their voice. It’s loud, it’s proud, it’s jocular (<em>goliardate</em>). And impossible to ignore. It shouldn’t be any other way.</p>
<p>The word <em>laurea</em>, meaning graduation, comes from laurel, and tradition dictates that the new graduate wears a laurel crown as a symbol of wisdom and achievement. These are often handmade by family or friends and customized with ribbons or charms in the graduate’s faculty colors.</p>
<p>Then begins the fun part: goliardic songs and the shout of “<em>Dottore! Dottore!</em>” echoing through the streets, bars, university halls, and restaurants. These spontaneous celebrations can last for hours, or until everyone loses their voice. It’s loud, it’s proud, it’s jocular (<em>goliardate</em>). And impossible to ignore. It shouldn’t be any other way. Graduation is a big deal!</p>
<p>A great cure for a sore throat? A good Spritz and probably a few more drinks after that. Next comes the family meal, where close friends often tag along. Don’t expect to leave anytime soon: there will be a first course, second course, dessert, espresso, and more aperitifs, sometimes stretching into the evening. If you’re lucky enough to be invited, come hungry and clear your calendar.</p>
<p>In cities like Padova, Trieste, or Bologna, family meals are often followed by a graduation party organized by friends.</p>
<p>These parties often include children’s games, playful punishments, and creative challenges. Some are held at home, while the bolder students opt for public spaces where the embarrassment is worse and the fun better. What one must have, especially for a Bachelor’s degree, is the <em>papiro</em> (a handmade, human-sized poster featuring a caricature of the graduate, filled with gossip, jokes, and a rhyming poem that <em>must</em> be read aloud). The reading is non-negotiable, but you can rely on the wine handed to you to ease the nerves.</p>
<p>There’s no official guide on how to survive an Italian graduation party, but one thing’s certain: From ridiculous costumes to wild dares involving strangers, anything can happen. The only rules are to record it all and have as much fun as possible.</p>
<p>Graduation is always a reason to show love and support. If it happens in summer, there’s double the cause for celebration. Just remember to choose your outfit wisely, because you don’t want to be sweating in every photo.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Culture</category>
  <category>Education</category>
  <guid>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-07-28 The Italian summer we don’t talk about/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-07-28 The Italian summer we don’t talk about/cover_xs.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="79" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A “well-integrated” Italian?</title>
  <link>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-06-26 A “well-integrated” Italian/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-06-26 A “well-integrated” Italian/cover_xl.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>When I first applied for my residence permit in Italy, I signed an agreement stating that I would commit to becoming well-integrated into Italian life within two years. But I had no clue what “well-integrated” was supposed to mean. Not a single person at the <em>questura</em> (or local police headquarters) explained anything about it. In fact, it was only months later that I found out that I had made this promise to become well-integrated.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Editor’s Note: For the purposes of this essay, this issue of assimilation should be considered distinct from any Italian citizenship concerns through the jus sanguinis, or descendent blood line law, which has had some changes of late, as well as aside from the hot-button issue of refugees, political asylum, or labor-trafficking embedded in Law No.&nbsp;187/2024.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>After a quick Google search, I found out about the percorso d’integrazione obbligatorio, a mandatory path or credit system that applies to every non-Italian above the age of sixteen who arrives in the country for the first time. It’s almost like a video game: you start with sixteen points, and the goal is to acquire at least thirty points by completing specific tasks. If you don’t meet the requirements within a certain timeframe, you lose points. <em>Fair enough</em>, I thought.</p>
<p>The list includes things like taking language or cultural classes, earning a degree, or buying a house. Although the first two sound very reasonable, I began to wonder how achievable all of this is for most people. I’m a Spanish speaker, I have an Italian partner, and I already hold a degree, all of which gives me a theoretical advantage over other immigrants who might be struggling to understand where to start. Bureaucracy is often slow and confusing. Perhaps that’s the real game.</p>
<p>Nobody ever said that immigrating was easy. It’s a process, and it takes time — more for some, less for others. Immigrant, for me and the dictionary, means coming to live permanently in a country in which you were not born. Your genes, race, story, motivations, and future plans don’t count once you land. All immigrants become people who hope to feel at home again.</p>
<p>Home is where you can relax and be yourself. Your safe place. It doesn’t have to be a place, really. It can be a feeling you carry with you.</p>
<p>While having all these thoughts, I found myself wondering again: <em>What does it mean to be well-integrated?</em> Is it just speaking the language fluently and hiding your accent? Is it being able to cook Italian food like a local and eat it every single day? Or maybe becoming a regular at the neighborhood bar and ordering your drink in dialect? Is it about becoming Italian in the legal sense?</p>
<p>I thought of a friend. She’s 26, almost 27, and has lived here for 20 years, attending school her entire life in Italy. She pays taxes and owns a home. She speaks Italian — and the Triestine dialect — without a hint of an accent. She also runs a business, which creates a lot of jobs for many people. And yet, legally, she’s not Italian.</p>
<p>Does she feel well-integrated? It’s hard to say. Too Colombian for Italy, too Italian for Colombia. Something’s missing.</p>
<p>To be well-integrated, do you have to give up your identity completely?</p>
<p>In early 2025, I had the chance to participate in the Latitudes project with other immigrants from Latin-America living in Europe. On Monday, we arrived as strangers. One week later, we left as a family, bound by a connection that felt completely natural. Maybe it was the food, the dancing, the shared language, the jokes, or the joy of reliving similar experiences.</p>
<p>Being born as a person from Latin America means growing up with the same kind of mom, the same neighborhood adventures, the same strict schoolteachers, the same <em>quinceañera</em> parties, the same unforgettable house parties full of dancing and gossip. We discovered that it’s impossible to forget who you were before arriving in Italy. We are immigrants, and our identity migrates with us. We are Latinos in Europe, but Latin America lives inside each of us.</p>
<p>I don’t really know when you get to feel “well-integrated,” but I’m sure you’ll recognize it by the laughter and the warmth of the hugs you’ll receive in your new home.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Culture</category>
  <category>Society</category>
  <category>Life in Italy</category>
  <guid>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-06-26 A “well-integrated” Italian/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-06-26 A “well-integrated” Italian/cover_xs.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="79" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>In the city of coffee</title>
  <link>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-07-01 coffee in Trieste/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-07-01 coffee in Trieste/cover.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Italy is renowned for its coffee shops on every corner. This devotion to coffee, however, is taken to a whole different level in Trieste. Trieste was one of the first European cities to open the&nbsp;<em>botteghe da caffè</em>. In the 1700s, these coffeehouses became popular as meeting places for politicians, artists, journalists, writers, and intellectuals. The city’s strategic location between what was once the Austro-Hungarian Empire and Slovenia meant that it was a key entry point for the high-quality green coffee beans coming from Asia, South America, and Africa. Trieste is also the birthplace of the renowned Illy company, a pioneer in espresso machine innovation.</p>
<p>In all this time, not much has changed in terms of coffee. Trieste’s inhabitants are very proud of the history and culture that have taken place in their cafés. Like many Italians, they love their coffee. And to make sure that everyone is aware just how important coffee is to them, they’ve made coffee drinking their thing.</p>
<p>If you want to order like a true Triestino, you will need a dictionary first. Here’s a quick guide, in case you don’t have one.</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Nero:</strong> A standard espresso served in a small cup.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Capo:</strong> A version of a cappuccino with just a touch of milk, similar to an espresso macchiato.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Gocciato</strong>: An espresso with a small drop of milk foam on top.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>These are just a few of the dozens of combinations you can order. To really impress your Italian server, ask for the capo in b (same as capo but in a glass). They will be surprised to see that a tourist unaccompanied by a local seems to know about this classic coffee.</p>
<p>But where can you savor this experience?</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Food</category>
  <category>Travel</category>
  <category>Coffee</category>
  <guid>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-07-01 coffee in Trieste/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-07-01 coffee in Trieste/cover_xs.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="79" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
