<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Valentina Salcedo</title>
<link>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.32</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Eating vs. eating</title>
  <link>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-09-20 Eating vs. eating/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-09-20 Eating vs. eating/cover_xl.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Is there a difference between eating because you have to and eating because you love food? I think there is, and that summer highlights this difference in a way no other season does.</p>
<p>Of course, we all need filling, nutritious meals if we are to function — at least 1,600 calories a day. But when eating becomes an experience to savor, to remember, and to share, then chewing and swallowing becomes a joy.</p>
<p>When I first moved to Italy, I was surprised by how much people talk about food. Italians don’t just eat. They love food. And they are very proud of their cuisine. It’s quite normal to hear a group of friends debating the cooking times of a recipe, or to arrive early to someone’s house to help in the kitchen, chatting while sampling appetizers as the main meal is being cooked.</p>
<p>Meals are are culture. They are lessons. Italian children learn basic cooking by observing, listening, and sometimes helping their moms.</p>
<p>Food is part of every plan, whether that is a day at the beach, a weekend trip, or a visit to a friend’s house. The questions, <em>“What should we bring? What are they making?”</em>, always come up.</p>
<p>It was summer when I arrived in Italy. I felt like I was being hugged by a mother. Within weeks, friends of friends (and even their families) knew not only my name, but also what food I liked, what I cooked, and what I absolutely couldn’t resist.</p>
<p>Here are some of the tastes that make me long for next summer:</p>
<section id="watermelon-cocktail" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="watermelon-cocktail">Watermelon cocktail</h3>
<p>Perfect for an aperitivo or BBQ. This never fails to win over friends, and is ideal in hot weather.</p>
<p>Cut a watermelon in half, scoop out the fruit, and mix it with strawberries, peaches, kiwi, grapes, sugar syrup, and vodka. Let it rest in the fridge for at least three hours (overnight is even better). Serve chilled in cups or directly from the watermelon shell.</p>
</section>
<section id="summer-salad" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summer-salad">Summer salad</h3>
<p>Great when the last thing you want is to cook. Slice ripe tomatoes, add cubes of Greek cheese, drizzle with olive oil, season with salt and pepper, and chill briefly. Fresh, quick, and satisfying.</p>
<p>Back in Colombia, food often felt like an obligation. I ate so I’d have the energy to study, but eating a meal never felt fulfilling. I was constantly in need of snacks between meals — chocolate, chips, anything quick. Cooking itself felt more burdensome than comforting. But in Italy, it’s different; here food means fried seafood with lemon, a community table where someone will serve me something that is both delicious and lovingly prepared when I am feeling too blase to cook for myself. And that has taught me to see food differently. I no longer eat to get by; I eat because food delights my senses. To eat because you love is different. Eating out of love is the life I want.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Food</category>
  <category>Culture</category>
  <guid>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-09-20 Eating vs. eating/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-09-20 Eating vs. eating/cover_xs.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="79" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Italian summer we don’t talk about</title>
  <link>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-07-28 The Italian summer we don’t talk about/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-07-28 The Italian summer we don’t talk about/cover_xl.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>If you’re a 2000s baby, you probably grew up with films like “The Lizzie McGuire Movie” or “Call Me by Your Name.” Summer flings, Vespa rides, and sunburns are often the first things that come to mind when we imagine Italy in July or August. But that’s not the whole picture for Gen Z Italians.</p>
<p>For many young Italians, these months are very intense. Some are preparing for the university entrance exams. Others are splitting their days between quick beach trips and long hours at the library. And the luckiest ones? They’re celebrating the end of this chapter with a full-blown <em>festa di laurea</em>.</p>
<p>Graduation day is one of the most anticipated moments for any university student, anywhere in the world. Unlike the stressful summer exam season, this is a time of joy and release.</p>
<p>Italian universities don’t typically host a big ceremony with caps and gowns. The event is intimate and personal. And to keep things exciting, on the same day there’s still one final hurdle: defending your thesis in front of friends, family, and a panel of professors, who announce your final grade on the spot. Only then are you officially <em>laureato</em> (you hold a degree).</p>
<p>These spontaneous celebrations can last for hours, or until everyone loses their voice. It’s loud, it’s proud, it’s jocular (<em>goliardate</em>). And impossible to ignore. It shouldn’t be any other way.</p>
<p>The word <em>laurea</em>, meaning graduation, comes from laurel, and tradition dictates that the new graduate wears a laurel crown as a symbol of wisdom and achievement. These are often handmade by family or friends and customized with ribbons or charms in the graduate’s faculty colors.</p>
<p>Then begins the fun part: goliardic songs and the shout of “<em>Dottore! Dottore!</em>” echoing through the streets, bars, university halls, and restaurants. These spontaneous celebrations can last for hours, or until everyone loses their voice. It’s loud, it’s proud, it’s jocular (<em>goliardate</em>). And impossible to ignore. It shouldn’t be any other way. Graduation is a big deal!</p>
<p>A great cure for a sore throat? A good Spritz and probably a few more drinks after that. Next comes the family meal, where close friends often tag along. Don’t expect to leave anytime soon: there will be a first course, second course, dessert, espresso, and more aperitifs, sometimes stretching into the evening. If you’re lucky enough to be invited, come hungry and clear your calendar.</p>
<p>In cities like Padova, Trieste, or Bologna, family meals are often followed by a graduation party organized by friends.</p>
<p>These parties often include children’s games, playful punishments, and creative challenges. Some are held at home, while the bolder students opt for public spaces where the embarrassment is worse and the fun better. What one must have, especially for a Bachelor’s degree, is the <em>papiro</em> (a handmade, human-sized poster featuring a caricature of the graduate, filled with gossip, jokes, and a rhyming poem that <em>must</em> be read aloud). The reading is non-negotiable, but you can rely on the wine handed to you to ease the nerves.</p>
<p>There’s no official guide on how to survive an Italian graduation party, but one thing’s certain: From ridiculous costumes to wild dares involving strangers, anything can happen. The only rules are to record it all and have as much fun as possible.</p>
<p>Graduation is always a reason to show love and support. If it happens in summer, there’s double the cause for celebration. Just remember to choose your outfit wisely, because you don’t want to be sweating in every photo.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Culture</category>
  <category>Education</category>
  <guid>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-07-28 The Italian summer we don’t talk about/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-07-28 The Italian summer we don’t talk about/cover_xs.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="79" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A “well-integrated” Italian?</title>
  <link>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-06-26 A “well-integrated” Italian/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-06-26 A “well-integrated” Italian/cover_xl.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>When I first applied for my residence permit in Italy, I signed an agreement stating that I would commit to becoming well-integrated into Italian life within two years. But I had no clue what “well-integrated” was supposed to mean. Not a single person at the <em>questura</em> (or local police headquarters) explained anything about it. In fact, it was only months later that I found out that I had made this promise to become well-integrated.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled" title="Editor’s Note">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Editor’s Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>For the purposes of this essay, this issue of assimilation should be considered distinct from any Italian citizenship concerns through the jus sanguinis, or descendent blood line law, which has had some changes of late, as well as aside from the hot-button issue of refugees, political asylum, or labor-trafficking embedded in Law No.&nbsp;187/2024.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>After a quick Google search, I found out about the percorso d’integrazione obbligatorio, a mandatory path or credit system that applies to every non-Italian above the age of sixteen who arrives in the country for the first time. It’s almost like a video game: you start with sixteen points, and the goal is to acquire at least thirty points by completing specific tasks. If you don’t meet the requirements within a certain timeframe, you lose points. <em>Fair enough</em>, I thought.</p>
<p>The list includes things like taking language or cultural classes, earning a degree, or buying a house. Although the first two sound very reasonable, I began to wonder how achievable all of this is for most people. I’m a Spanish speaker, I have an Italian partner, and I already hold a degree, all of which gives me a theoretical advantage over other immigrants who might be struggling to understand where to start. Bureaucracy is often slow and confusing. Perhaps that’s the real game.</p>
<p>Nobody ever said that immigrating was easy. It’s a process, and it takes time — more for some, less for others. Immigrant, for me and the dictionary, means coming to live permanently in a country in which you were not born. Your genes, race, story, motivations, and future plans don’t count once you land. All immigrants become people who hope to feel at home again.</p>
<p>Home is where you can relax and be yourself. Your safe place. It doesn’t have to be a place, really. It can be a feeling you carry with you.</p>
<p>While having all these thoughts, I found myself wondering again: <em>What does it mean to be well-integrated?</em> Is it just speaking the language fluently and hiding your accent? Is it being able to cook Italian food like a local and eat it every single day? Or maybe becoming a regular at the neighborhood bar and ordering your drink in dialect? Is it about becoming Italian in the legal sense?</p>
<p>I thought of a friend. She’s 26, almost 27, and has lived here for 20 years, attending school her entire life in Italy. She pays taxes and owns a home. She speaks Italian — and the Triestine dialect — without a hint of an accent. She also runs a business, which creates a lot of jobs for many people. And yet, legally, she’s not Italian.</p>
<p>Does she feel well-integrated? It’s hard to say. Too Colombian for Italy, too Italian for Colombia. Something’s missing.</p>
<p>To be well-integrated, do you have to give up your identity completely?</p>
<p>In early 2025, I had the chance to participate in the Latitudes project with other immigrants from Latin-America living in Europe. On Monday, we arrived as strangers. One week later, we left as a family, bound by a connection that felt completely natural. Maybe it was the food, the dancing, the shared language, the jokes, or the joy of reliving similar experiences.</p>
<p>Being born as a person from Latin America means growing up with the same kind of mom, the same neighborhood adventures, the same strict schoolteachers, the same <em>quinceañera</em> parties, the same unforgettable house parties full of dancing and gossip. We discovered that it’s impossible to forget who you were before arriving in Italy. We are immigrants, and our identity migrates with us. We are Latinos in Europe, but Latin America lives inside each of us.</p>
<p>I don’t really know when you get to feel “well-integrated,” but I’m sure you’ll recognize it by the laughter and the warmth of the hugs you’ll receive in your new home.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Culture</category>
  <category>Society</category>
  <category>Life in Italy</category>
  <guid>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-06-26 A “well-integrated” Italian/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-06-26 A “well-integrated” Italian/cover_xs.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="79" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>In the city of coffee</title>
  <link>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-07-01 coffee in Trieste/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-07-01 coffee in Trieste/cover_xl.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Italy is renowned for its coffee shops on every corner. This devotion to coffee, however, is taken to a whole different level in Trieste. Trieste was one of the first European cities to open the&nbsp;<em>botteghe da caffè</em>. In the 1700s, these coffeehouses became popular as meeting places for politicians, artists, journalists, writers, and intellectuals. The city’s strategic location between what was once the Austro-Hungarian Empire and Slovenia meant that it was a key entry point for the high-quality green coffee beans coming from Asia, South America, and Africa. Trieste is also the birthplace of the renowned Illy company, a pioneer in espresso machine innovation.</p>
<p>In all this time, not much has changed in terms of coffee. Trieste’s inhabitants are very proud of the history and culture that have taken place in their cafés. Like many Italians, they love their coffee. And to make sure that everyone is aware just how important coffee is to them, they’ve made coffee drinking their thing.</p>
<p>If you want to order like a true Triestino, you will need a dictionary first. Here’s a quick guide, in case you don’t have one.</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Nero:</strong> A standard espresso served in a small cup.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Capo:</strong> A version of a cappuccino with just a touch of milk, similar to an espresso macchiato.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Gocciato</strong>: An espresso with a small drop of milk foam on top.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>These are just a few of the dozens of combinations you can order. To really impress your Italian server, ask for the capo in b (same as capo but in a glass). They will be surprised to see that a tourist unaccompanied by a local seems to know about this classic coffee.</p>
<p>But where can you savor this experience?</p>
<p>After arriving by cruise ship, you should make your first stop the Piazza Unità d’Italia, Trieste’s grand main square. Here, you’ll find the famous “Caffè degli Specchi” with its long queue of eager tourists. For just one euro at the counter, you can sample one of the many coffee variations displayed on a one-meter menu, each item featuring a photo and name, so you shouldn’t be too perplexed.</p>
<p>For those seeking a more refined experience, try visiting historic cafés like Caffè San Marco, where you can spend an entire afternoon immersed in culture and literature (the café even houses its own open library). Alternatively, lovers of classy coffee-drinking atmospheres will adore Caffè Tommaseo, with its dreamy neoclassical interiors accented by Belgian mirrors, a perfect haven if you want a leisurely, inspirational morning.</p>
<p>Choosing the right spot in a city famed for its coffee can seem tricky. Whether you’re drawn to the bustling, traditional bars or the serene, art-filled cafés, remember that each venue has great choices.</p>
<p>Don’t get fooled by long queues — if one café is busy, there are many others waiting to offer you a really good coffee.</p>
<p>Even Triestinos leave their customary bar once in a while to explore other options in their city. And remember, un caffè al banco (coffee at the bar) tastes better with company.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Food</category>
  <category>Travel</category>
  <category>Coffee</category>
  <guid>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-07-01 coffee in Trieste/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-07-01 coffee in Trieste/cover_xs.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="79" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Goodbye, my little princess</title>
  <link>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-03-29 Goodbye, my little princess/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-03-29 Goodbye, my little princess/cover_xl.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>My mom thinks time stopped when I took that plane. But it hasn’t. I’m closer to my mid-twenties than to my teenage years. I’ve made sacrifices along the way, and now, I’m building the life I once dreamed of as a little girl.</p>
<p>I’m living <em>la dolce vita</em> — with everything that comes with it. Coffee is a must in my sweet breakfasts. I order a small <em>caffè al banco</em> (coffee at the counter) at least twice a day. I’ve learned to enjoy the calmness of doing things at a slower pace. And my biggest joy? Savoring every meal.</p>
<p>But I hesitate before picking up when I see my mom calling. Not because I’m a terrible daughter, but because, in her eyes, I’m still fifteen. No matter how many conversations we’ve had, every call goes the same way:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“How are you, and why haven’t you called me?” “I was busy. I study, remember?” “The whole day?” “No, I clean, cook, and have hobbies too.” “That’s why you come home so late! Who are you going out with? Send me their numbers in case I need to reach you.” “Are you planning to text them in Italian?” Silence.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And let’s not even talk about what happens if I say I’m not doing “very good.” It’s always been like that, but moving abroad has made it worse. The seven-hour time difference makes it even harder to reply in real time.</p>
<p>I left home at twenty, eager to explore, to carve my own path, to find myself. For the past two years, I’ve been living in Italy. I’m not on an extended vacation — this is my life now. Italian isn’t just a casual language I struggle with; it’s the local language of my home. Instead of hiding in my cave — my <em>monolocale</em>, a flat shared with my significant other — I’ve joined Pilates groups, associations, and volunteering communities.</p>
<p>I understand the untranslatable jokes now. I use dialect words to emphasize a point. And last month, I made it official: I changed my WhatsApp number to +39.</p>
<p>I’ve dealt with never-ending bureaucracy, waited outside the <em>questura</em> (local police station) for hours, struggled to explain symptoms at the pharmacy, and faced the loneliness that comes with starting over. And yet, every time I call home, I’m still her little princess.</p>
<p>What’s more adult than moving abroad on your own? Moving abroad without a mother telling you to be strong.</p>
<p>It’s been rough. There have been good days. Bad days. Just days. Moving abroad is often romanticized as adventurous, thrilling, full of opportunities. And while it is all those things, it’s also a process of grief.</p>
<p>You mourn your past life — the ease of your native language, the comfort of old friendships, the familiarity of home. Every new experience is exciting but also slightly foreign. The first time you navigate the local supermarket, order coffee without hesitation, or save a new friend’s number in your phone, you realize you’re slowly building something new.</p>
<p>Adulthood doesn’t come with a clear marker. It’s not just turning eighteen or paying bills. It’s making decisions no one else can make for you. It’s standing in a foreign country, trying to explain your symptoms to a doctor in a language you’re still learning. It’s crying the night before a job interview, doubting yourself, and showing up anyway.</p>
<p>Moving abroad in your twenties is amazing. And it sucks. At first, I felt an intense need to call my mom. But I knew if I told her everything, she’d worry. The first time I broke down, she would have told me to take the first flight home. That wasn’t an option.</p>
<p>What’s more adult than moving abroad on your own? Moving abroad without a mother telling you to be strong. I filter out the hard days, the doubt, the exhaustion. Because if I tell her the truth, she’ll feel helpless — and then I’ll have to comfort her too.</p>
<p>I love my mom. I know she misses me. I miss her too. But I don’t want our relationship to be built on nostalgia for who I was; I want her to see me for who I am. She can still call me <em>baby</em>, but I hope she also recognizes that I’m no longer one.</p>
<p>So, Mom, please let me live my way, and I promise I’ll call more.</p>
<p>I love you, Your big girl</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Society</category>
  <category>Personal</category>
  <guid>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-03-29 Goodbye, my little princess/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-03-29 Goodbye, my little princess/cover_xs.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="79" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>15-minute connection</title>
  <link>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-02-01 15-minute connection/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-02-01 15-minute connection/cover_xl.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The challenge of making friends with people who already have their own group of friends — now, that might be something you thought you wouldn’t have to deal with once you’d left your university days behind. That is, until you pack twenty years of life — or more — into a 48 pound suitcase and get on a plane to Italy.</p>
<p>Italians are kind and warm people. The catch? You have to get in first.</p>
<p>Making friends in Trieste has not exactly been easy. Which is why I convinced myself that volunteering might help. Maybe, if luck was on my side, I might find a friend there.</p>
<p>The easiest part was signing to become a volunteer. I filled out an online questionnaire. After one month, I received an email confirming the details. Two and a half months, one meeting, and one Telegram group later, here I am — surviving.</p>
<p>The winner among all these volunteer activities? The Trieste Film Festival. It brings together international films, filmmakers, and cinema lovers from Central and Eastern Europe.</p>
<p>However, being an “International Film Festival” doesn’t mean international staff. On the first day, I found myself on the social media team (which, apart from yours truly, is native speakers only) struggling to finish sentences in Italian.</p>
<p>On my application, I’d written, “I am a journalist with a social media background. I enjoy teamwork.” What I forgot to mention? My Italian is comparable to that of a toddler’s.</p>
<p>People were running around, shouting into phones. Some volunteers were missing. Conversations, as heard by me, went like this: “The posters haven’t arrived. Who has a microphone? Where’s Giulia? Let’s try your phone!”</p>
<p>On the other side of the room, I tried to explain that I didn’t know what to do or who I was working with. But I didn’t want to interrupt the chaos, so I stayed quiet.</p>
<p>Someone said my name. Lost, I responded, “Yes, that’s me.” No, I didn’t have a microphone. Yes, I will do the interviews. No, just in English. It’s better to leave my broken Italian off camera. Funny, as my English is not perfect either, but at least they won’t know.</p>
<p>“We are two,” said the tipsy self in my head to my tipsy self.</p>
<p>After a quick introduction, I was left at a bar table in the theater with another volunteer, Alexandra. Since the microphone didn’t work, we had nothing to do. We exchanged small talk before the silence settled between us.</p>
<p>Later, Alexandra and I were assigned to read synopses of short films and draft questions. A blonde girl arrived, placed a few books on the table, and began analyzing the plots.</p>
<p>I struggled to follow in Italian but didn’t want to slow things down by asking for English translations. After a while, I managed to tell them, in my very limited vocabulary, what I thought. Though far from perfect, it felt good to be part of the conversation.</p>
<p>By half past nine, we had planned more than fifteen interviews and reviewed posts, DMs, and comments, and even helped a 19-year-old video editor who seemed to be a natural tech genius. And yet, I had spent two hours doing nothing, unless wandering around the room counts.</p>
<p>To pass the time, I had a snack and fantasized that I was fluent in Italian.</p>
<p>Finally, a not work-related thing happened. I don’t know if it was the boredom, the tiredness, or the medium-sized beer that I’d bought for three euros, but I had a 15-minute talk with another volunteer. It was amazing. He was coming back from London, where he’d been living for the last five years, and now felt like he didn’t belong here anymore. Yet he didn’t belong there either. “We are two,” said the tipsy self in my head to my tipsy self.</p>
<p>We laughed about how our careers and lives felt like a “disaster,” just like everyone else who starts working in media or art. That little moment of connection was all I was looking for. Just a shared laugh, a comment or two about the messy work day, just that tiny hint that we are not alone.</p>
<p>I grabbed my coat, said goodbye, and messaged my boyfriend.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Life in Italy</category>
  <category>Trieste</category>
  <category>Personal</category>
  <guid>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-02-01 15-minute connection/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2025-02-01 15-minute connection/cover_xs.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="79" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Horrors of December</title>
  <link>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2024-12-28 Horrors of December/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2024-12-28 Horrors of December/cover_xl.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>You may consider the Christmas season a time of fun, and while most Christmas traditions are sweet, especially the ones for little children, like sipping hot chocolate in pajamas while watching Disney movies, there is one tradition in the mountains of northeast Italy that is reserved exclusively for the naughtiest of naughty little kids. The night of the Krampus.</p>
<p>According to legend, one day early in December, a figure half-goat, half-demon arrives. He has horns on his head, a red tongue, and black hair. Sometimes he brings a basket in which he carries off the worst behaved. His main purpose is to punish those who haven’t behaved well this year. A sort of anti-Santa Claus. And with that kind of fear, who wouldn’t behave?</p>
<p>How the Krampus came about is unclear, but it seems the story has its roots in Germanic traditions. Some believe that once upon a time the Krampus and Saint Nicholas were two sides of the same person, delivering presents and chastisements, whichever was merited. Others suggest that he was Saint Nicholas’s helper, the bad cop to his good cop.</p>
<p>But in an instant the atmosphere shifted.</p>
<p>Out of nowhere, creatures part-bestial, part-humanoid monster charged through the crowd.</p>
<p>This December, I had the chance to experience my first, and probably last, Krampus run.</p>
<p>After a five-hour non-stop drive from Munich, I was happy to stop, even if just briefly, at a charming little town in the mountains. Later, I discovered we were already in Friuli-Venezia Giulia, just two hours from Trieste.</p>
<p>As a short person — 1.52 meters, to be precise — I can easily pass as a child.</p>
<p>The town square was packed, people standing to shoulder waiting for the event to begin. My first thought was, <em>This must be something truly funny</em>. And that wasn’t entirely wrong. The evening began with festive music, laughter, and the warm, spicy aroma of vin brulé filling the air.</p>
<p>But in an instant the atmosphere shifted.</p>
<p>Out of nowhere, creatures part-bestial, part-humanoid monster charged through the crowd. They were clad in elaborate costumes, some in fur, and all wielding weapons of various sorts: axes, chains, birch rods. I had come with no very clear notion of what the event entailed, and my confusion must have been apparent on my face, for my partner leaned in to explain what the Krampus was and that its only prey was children. So I relaxed. Briefly.</p>
<p>What I hadn’t accounted for was the fact that the children here were practically twice my size.</p>
<p>Despite the metal fence separating the performers from the crowd, chaos ensued when a mischievous 12 year old boy tried to hide near me. Before I knew it, I was on the receiving end of one of those birch rods. Let me tell you, I wasn’t afraid of their masks — I was afraid of my backside being hit again.</p>
<p>As the two-hour spectacle unfolded, I realized that the festival was nothing like the grim, fear-inducing ritual I’d imagined. Families gathered, children were thrilled, teenagers dared each other to get closer — and closer — to the Krampuses.</p>
<p>And so the business of the Krampuses is not just to scare the living daylights out of bad children, but to preserve an ancient tradition and bring the community together.</p>
<p>Still, I don’t think I’ll be attending another Krampus run anytime soon.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Life in Italy</category>
  <category>Traditions</category>
  <category>Culture</category>
  <guid>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2024-12-28 Horrors of December/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2024-12-28 Horrors of December/cover_xs.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="79" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Spotting Italians abroad</title>
  <link>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2024-11-25 Spotting Italians abroad/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2024-11-25 Spotting Italians abroad/cover_xl.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Until last year, I never thought Colombians and Italians had much in common. Then I met an Italian for the first time, in February 2023. I was in Málaga, Spain, on a desperate house hunt. I had arrived for an exchange program (Erasmus, as Europeans call it) and paid two months’ rent in advance.</p>
<p>Two days after moving in, my Spanish roommates broke the news that by the end of the month, I’d need to find somewhere else to live because the owner didn’t want to have students renting anymore. Furious but out of options, I started searching for another apartment. I scoured Facebook groups, WhatsApp groups, and agencies, looking for anything that might be available.</p>
<p>Luck, however, wasn’t on my side. Everything was already booked.</p>
<p>One morning, a real estate agent called Mrs.&nbsp;Mercedes rang. She told me to meet her on Larios Street at 3:15 and to wait at the blue building. Then she hung up before I’d even said thank you. So I got ready, grabbed a folder with all my documents, and went to see this Mrs.&nbsp;Mercedes.</p>
<p>One morning, a real estate agent called Mrs.&nbsp;Mercedes rang. She told me to meet her on Larios Street at 3:15 and to wait at the blue building.</p>
<p>When I arrived, I saw a group of at least ten people waiting near the blue wall. They all had similar features: jet-black hair, light skin, bright eyes. The girls were all made up and dressed to impress. I wondered if they were siblings or if they had another appointment after this one.</p>
<p>I snapped out of my thoughts when I heard Mrs.&nbsp;Mercedes greeting us. I looked up to see a middle-aged woman, short, with a few extra pounds, and a bob haircut. I can’t explain it, but I thought she looked just as she had sounded on the phone.</p>
<p>Mrs.&nbsp;Mercedes invited us to climb three narrow flights of stairs to see the apartment, which could be ours — or, well, someone’s. She greeted the current tenants, then proceeded to ignore them, and began showing us the three tiny rooms, the balcony with a view of the shopping center, a cramped kitchen, and a washing machine of questionable capability.</p>
<p>As we were leaving, she reminded us there were already other people interested, and whoever paid the two deposits and first month’s rent that day would get it.</p>
<p>The others in the group seemed annoyed when Mrs.&nbsp;Mercedes left. They started speaking in a language I didn’t understand, though it sounded close to Spanish. By their expressions and energetic hand gestures, I guessed it was about the apartment. And, being a bit nosy, I couldn’t help but chime in.</p>
<p>“Is everything okay? What’s the problem?” I asked.</p>
<p>No response, just weird looks.</p>
<p>“Maybe I can help . . .” I suggested.</p>
<p>A minute later, they stopped talking amongst themselves, and one of the guys looked at me.</p>
<p>“I need to find a place by tomorrow. My contract finishes today, and I haven’t found anything yet. I don’t want to be homeless until I find something.”</p>
<p>“Oh, that’s awful. I’ve seen a few places, but they’re out of my budget. Like six or, maybe, five hundred something.”</p>
<p>“Then, out of my budget, too,” he said, laughing wryly as he walked off.</p>
<p>I continued on my way to meet some friends until I realized someone else was walking alongside me. I turned and saw one of the other guys from the group.</p>
<p>“Do you and your friends have the same problem?” I asked.</p>
<p>“Nobody wants to rent us their house.”</p>
<p>“Why’s that? I don’t get it.”</p>
<p>“Because we’re Italians and they say we love to gamble.”</p>
<p>“And you didn’t <em>say</em> anything?”</p>
<p>“Well, I can’t promise to avoid something that I would probably do,” he laughed.</p>
<p>I stayed quiet, thinking about what he’d just said. Though I’d never been overtly discriminated against for my nationality, being Colombian carries a stigma that’s hard to hide, and it hurts to see someone else enduring similar prejudices.</p>
<p>That day, a seed of curiosity was planted in me. I was interested in understanding why Italians had such a “terrible” reputation. I wanted to know more about their culture. With that goal in mind, I slowly began to join their groups. I knew I’d need to be quiet and open-minded for them to trust me. Eventually, I was invited to a party.</p>
<p>What was the first thing I learned? That you can’t go unnoticed when you’re the only one who isn’t Italian at an Italian gathering. Not only did my appearance give me away, but my lack of fluency in the language did, too. Even though I spent hours nodding and listening to their conversations, I only understood about sixty percent.</p>
<p>I took my mission so seriously that I became a known feature at these gatherings. They knew my name, my address, and that I was terrible at holding my alcohol. And they knew also that I was hopelessly smitten with one of them.</p>
<p>It seems a basic rule in Italian culture: If you accept someone, you have to accept their romantic partners.</p>
<p>The reason I managed to “infiltrate” this crowd was that they’d allowed it from the beginning, once they saw that I was dating one of their group. It seems a basic rule in Italian culture: If you accept someone, you have to accept their romantic partners. Italians do not compartmentalize their relationships.</p>
<p>After six months of my little “investigation,” I came to a conclusion about why Italians aren’t welcomed as tenants in Spain. Italian Erasmus students are (in)famous for enjoying life. They go out more often than they attend class, they dance with their eyes closed (even if they can’t dance), they meet up with friends several times a week, and these gatherings often involve good food and drink. And lastly, they invite friends from Italy to stay with them on weekends to enjoy Spain together. Basically, they’re pretty much like Colombians on any normal day in Colombia: happy, living as if life were a big party, making friends on the journey, and, sometimes, stirring some trouble!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Culture</category>
  <category>Expats</category>
  <category>Personal</category>
  <guid>https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2024-11-25 Spotting Italians abroad/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://valentinasalcedo.github.io/articles/2024-11-25 Spotting Italians abroad/cover_xs.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="79" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
